Guide to the Edward Lewis Wallant Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward Lewis Wallant papers
1945-1977
YCAL MSS 606
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8
(11 boxes)
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, photographs, sketches, and awards that document the career of American author Edward Lewis Wallant. The bulk of the collection consists of drafts and proofs of novels and shorter writings, reviews, and related correspondence with publishers and literary agents. Much of the material post-dates Wallant's death and reflects his wife Joyce Fromkin Wallant's efforts to see his last two novels published and to manage his legacy in light of continued interest in his work. Photographs include portraits of Wallant as well as a few snapshots of his family and from his service in World War II. Writings of others include critical analysis and adaptations of Wallant's novels.
Wallant, Edward Lewis, 1926-1962
Wallant, Joyce Fromkin, d. 1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kim Wallant, Leslie Wallant, and Scott Wallant, 1991-2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 4-11 (December 2009 Acquisition): reproduction previously restricted until 2012 December 15.
Edward Lewis Wallant (1926-1962)
American novelist Edward Lewis Wallant was born on October 19, 1926, in New Haven, Connecticut, to Sol and Anna Mendel Wallant. Following service in the U.S. Navy, he was educated at the Unversity of Connecticut, Pratt Intstitute, and the New School for Social Research. He had a successful career in advertising, as an art director, alongside his work as a writer. His first novel, The Human Season (1960), won the National Jewish Book Award; his second, The Pawnbroker (1961), was nominated for the National Book Award and adapted into a film starring Rod Steiger. Wallant was awarded a Guggenheim fellowshop for 1962, and travelled to Europe. Shortly after his return, on December 6, 1962, he died suddenly of a stroke at the age of thirty-six. Two additional novels were published posthumously: The Tenants of Moonbloom (1963) and The Children at the Gate (1964).
Wallant married Joyce Fromkin in 1948. The couple had three children: Scott, Kim, and Leslie. At the time of Wallant's death the family was living in Norwalk, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, photographs, sketches, and awards that document the career of American author Edward Lewis Wallant. The bulk of the collection consists of drafts and proofs of novels and shorter writings, reviews, and related correspondence with publishers and literary agents. Much of the material post-dates Wallant's death and reflects his wife Joyce Fromkin Wallant's efforts to see his last two novels published and to manage his legacy in light of continued interest in his work. Photographs include portraits of Wallant as well as a few snapshots of his family and from his service in World War II. Writings of others include critical analysis and adaptations of Wallant's novels.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: September 1991 Acquisition and December 2009 Acquisition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Wallant, Edward Lewis, 1926-1962; Wallant, Joyce Fromkin, d. 1991
- September 1991 Acquisition, circa 1945-1977; 2.5; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three groups: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers
  - Correspondence
    - Wallant, Edward Lewis, 1949-62, n.d; 5 (Box 1)
    - Wallant, Joyce, 1948-73; 6 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Writings by Wallant
      - The Artist's Eyesight
        - Typescript, carbon, corrected, [1962] (Box 1)
        - Printed version, 1963 (Box 1)
      - The Children at the Gate
        - Page proofs, 1963 (Box 1)
        - Advance uncorrected proof, 1964 (Box 1)
        - Book jacket, undated (Box 1)
        - Correspondence, 1963-72 (Box 1)
        - Reviews, 1964 (Box 1)
          Related Archival Materials note
          Also stored in: Oversize, Box 3
      - Pawnbroker, Children at the Gate, The Tenants of Moonbloom: reviews, 2 (Box 1)
      - The Human Season: book jacket (Box 1)
      - The Pawnbroker (Box 1)
        - Book jacket, undated
        - Publicity (Box 1)
          Stored in: Oversize, Box 3
        - Reviews, 1963-65 (Box 1)
          Also stored in: Box 3
      - The Tenants of Moonbloom
        - Galleys, 1963 (Box 1)
        - Advance uncorrected proof, 1963 (Box 1)
        - Play: typescript, carbon, undated (Box 1)
        - Reviews, 1963-64 (Box 1)
    - Writings by others
      - Bitoun, Lazare. Edward Lewis Wallant: typescript, mimeograph, 1977 Jun (Box 2)
      - Epstein, Seymour. Wallant's Literary Legacy: printed version, 1965 (Box 2)
      - Mesher, David Ronald. The Novels of Edward Lewis Wallant: typescript, photocopy, undated (Box 2)
      - Raper, Anne Browning. Edward Lewis Wallant: A Critical Study: typescript, photocopy, 1968 (Box 2)
        Scope and Contents
        With: TLS to Joyce Malkin from Anne Browning Raper, 1968 Aug 17
      - Sartre, Jean-Paul. The Reprieve: printed version, annotated by Edward Lewis Wallant, 1960 (Box 2)
      - Wechter, Julius and Cissy. The Human Season: play, typescript, mimeograph, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Other Papers
    - Biographical material, 1948-73 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1960-66 (Box 2)
    - Edward Lewis Wallant Memorial Book Award, 1963, undated (Box 2)
    - Fragments, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Harry and Ethel Daroff Memorial Fiction Award, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, circa 1945-1963, undated (Box 2)
    - Sketchbook, undated (Box 2)
    - Vital records and official documents, 1948-63 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified
  - Oversize
    - Writings
      - The Children at the Gate and Tenants of Moonbloom
        - Reviews, 1963 (Box 3 (Oversize))
      - The Pawnbroker
        - Book jacket, undated (Box 3 (Oversize))
        - Publicity, undated (Box 3 (Oversize))
        - Reviews and publicity for movie, 1965 (Box 3 (Oversize))
    - Other Papers
      - Harry and Ethel Daroff Memorial Award (Box 3 (Oversize))
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3 (Oversize))
      - Unidentified (Box 3 (Oversize))
- December 2009 Acquisition, circa 1960s; 5.5; (8 boxes)
  Organized into two groups: Writings and Other Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Reproduction previously restricted until 2012 December 15.
  - Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - An Artist's Eyesight (Box 4)
    - Birth (Box 4)
    - The Children at the Gate, 8 (Box 4)
    - The Days to Come (Box 4)
    - Death of an Enemy, 2 (Box 4)
    - Father and Child (Box 4)
    - The Fathers, 2 (Box 4)
    - Fight Night (Box 4)
    - [Gimple] (Box 4)
    - Second Draft [Gimple?] (Box 4)
    - Gimple the Beast, 6 (Box 5)
    - Gimple and Harold, 2 (Box 5)
    - Harold and Gimple (Box 5)
    - The Ground Glass View - Chapters 1-9, 2 (Box 5)
    - "Berman" aka The Human Season (Box 5)
    - The Human Season, 2 (Box 5)
    - The Human Season, galley proofs (Box 9 (Oversize))
    - Life is a Fountain (Box 6)
    - Odyssey of a Middleman (Part I) (Box 6)
    - Odyssey of a Middleman (Part II) (Box 6)
    - The Pawnbroker - Chapter Outline (Box 6)
    - Pawnbroker Setting T(c), 2 (Box 6)
    - The Pawnbroker - Setting T(carbon) (Box 6)
    - The Pawnbroker, galley proofs (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - The Pawnbroker, galley proofs (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - A Portrait of the Artist, as an Artist Part II (Box 6)
    - The Quest - Draft (Box 6)
    - Tannenbaum's Journey, 2 (Box 6)
    - Tarzan's Cottage, 5 (Box 7)
    - The Tenants of Moonbloom, 6 (Box 7)
    - View of a Marvelous City, 2 (Box 8)
    - The Way to Spain (Box 8)
    - Manuscript [Willy?] (Box 8)
    - Second version "Willy" (Box 8)
    - Untitled manuscripts, 3 (Box 8)
  - Other Papers
    - Manuscript notes by Wickenden (Box 8)
    - Drawings (Box 8)
    - Binder Covers with Sketches (Box 8)
    - Photograph of Wallant at drafting table (Box 8)